<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>temporal on Remko Duursma</title>
    <link>/tags/temporal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in temporal on Remko Duursma</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/temporal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of fuel prices in New South Wales</title>
      <link>/post/2018-01-24-fuelprices1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-01-24-fuelprices1/</guid>
      <description>How do petrol prices vary across the state?The price of fuel at service stations varies tremendously, both in space - across the large Australian state of New South Wales, and time - with surprising patterns. In this post I begin my quest to understand how fuel price varies, what factors explain its fluctuation over time and spatial variation. Obviously it would be nice to be able to know where to drive for cheaper fuel (what kind of areas are cheaper?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fuel prices in New South Wales - Part 2</title>
      <link>/post/2018-01-24-fuelprices2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-01-24-fuelprices2/</guid>
      <description>It is no secret that gasoline and diesel prices at the pump vary from day to day and from one place to the next. Few people are aware though that a typical pattern in fuel prices looks like this:
Newspaper articles have written about this pattern, web services exist that show where you are on the cycle, and you can compare main cities across Australia. In Sydney, the cycle is about 30 days long (more about that later), and the timing of the spike increase in fuel (which takes only 2-3 days) varies little from pump to pump.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>